<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section
  id=""
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
>
<title>The Design Process</title>
<note>
Although my talk is intended to be about Mr. Goff, this portion of it is
going to be understandings of design that are mine alone and not intended
to tell you "how BG worked".  He would not appreciate that, and never did it
himself.  Rather they might be described as "Observations about the design
process prompted by my association with Bruce Goff", and the evidence that
they have some relationship to what he thought and did is the fact that
I did in fact have a close association and opportunity to observe and
participate over a number of years.
</note>
<section>
<title>Aesthetics</title>
<para>
Of course a primary goal was that the buildings should be aesthetically
pleasing in their completed as-built setting.  In fact his interest strongly
seemed to be in seeing that the actual experience of being within the
actual building was the predominant goal, rather than merely creating
beautiful patterns on paper.
</para>
<section>
<title>More than mere form: BG and Varese</title>
<para>
Toward the beginning of our assocation, in 1958, the electonic poem at the
Brussel's World Fair had been created by Corbusier and Edgard Varese,
and we often dicussed this building specifically.  I also had the distinct
pleasure of visiting Varese in his brownstone in "the Village" along
with BG, and listening (and very timidly even participating) while he
and Varese discussed it.  It was BG's first meeting with Varese since this
work had been done (in a later meeting we also discussed Deserts. a
composition done at Bell Laboratories by Varese for which apparently
some critic suggest he be "sent to an electric chair").
</para>
<note>
<para>
During the first of the 2 conversations with Varese, and as a response
(greatly undeserved) to my playing of recordings of electronic music
I had created with instruments I had designed and build - solder and tubes,
whatever those are for the younger among you), he carefully took out
from a drawer the original manuscript of Debussy's La Mer - the most
sacred of all music to Mr. Goff - which Debussy had given to him
personally.  It was tear-stained when Debussy had cried upon learning
of the death of his mother.
</para>
<para>
That occurence was brought to mind when reading in the referenced paper
of Debussy's early encouragement of Varese (trained as a mathematician):
"Rules do not make a work of art.  You have the right to compose what
you want to, the way you want to." What could better describe the view
of Bruce Goff!
</para>
</note>
<para>
BG thought this building (a temporary structure for the fair, unfortunately)
exemplified actual existent architecture rather than "just drawings",
and we discussed how this attempt to integrate musical and spatial flow
might signify new possibilities for design of both.
</para>
<para>
The point in part is that this was a building designed to show the
possibilities for that integration, not just for its visual aesthetic
appeal, and that the form was a result of the problem, in fact Corbu's attempt
to encapsulate the music in a particular setting.
</para>
<para>Here is a nice page on
<ulink url="http://personal-pages.lvc.edu/~snyder/em/varese.html">
Edgar Varese: Father of Electronic Music</ulink>
including toward the end a description
of the two works just mentioned.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Appearance and Reality: BG and Gaudi</title>
<para>
As it happened, and luckily for me, my initial acquaintance with BG and
early involvment in Bartlesville with this world new to me, coincided
in part with a period in which a former student Thad Kuzmierski (pardon the spelling which is unlikely to be correct) was in Barcelona on a Guggenheim
Fellowship, with the enthusiastic endorsement of Mr. Goff, to study the
work of this incredible architect.  We would all breathlessly await the
coming of the latest information and especially photographs, and then eagerly
study the designs and other information about what and why and when.
One has to realize that there was not at that time much information available
in this country, or even in Spain, about the  man and his work, and much
of it was all the same.  As contact was made and we learned for example
about the Amigos and their work, it was all quite exciting.
</para>
<para>
In respect for me the most important aspect was that as an "outsider" I
was totally unaware of any controversy about the man and his work, held
no opinions except "I've never been so astounded", and I was able to observe
and form opinions about BG's reactions to the work, which of course he had
known of for years.  This also led to a large number of discussions of
a variety of topics such as "Wright's opinions of Gaudi" (I suspect the
phrase "architecture with a laxative" may already be well-known), or one
that was interesting to me "Did Louis Sullivan know of Gaudi and what did
he think or would he have thought?".
</para>
<para>
As someone with a particular interest in structural engineering I was pleased
to learn more - some of it later on - of Gaudi's many engineering accomplishemts in his buildings, and to discuss that aspect of his work with BG. I defy you
to find anyone who doesn't love those buildings, unless they are too "academic" or too "stuck in the mud" or "afraid" to admit their appreciation.  But what
was at the time and has later become even more interesting to me was the fact
that BG did not only focus on the aesthetics: we discussed how much the
engineering and the aesthetics (I will not say the engineering and the architecture since he - and I - did not distinguish) fit together.  He did not see the
"ornament" as applied, he saw it as "organic" in the sense of grown out of the
problem, and did not mean that only in some simple sense that it appeared to
be "growing" but in a much more abstract sense.
</para>
<para>
Later we learned of the "strings in the basement"
and I was able to help (I hope) BG understand the real nature and the real power of this technique, and the
whole notion of "isostatic structures" fascinated me, as an abstract concept
exemplified in actual structures, which were literally produced by performing
the kind of thing that mathematicians love to do.  That is, find a concept
(lines of force), take your understanding of it in one setting (strings
don't handle compression well, so you know hanging strings are isostatic
in handling only tension, and then turn that understanding into an understanding
of exactly the same thing (structures made of stone which cannot handle tension very well).  And it worked.
</para>
<para>
We discussed this at length in terms of ways this kind of understanding
could help in the training of architects, especially in the "Kebyar" setting
that was often his dream.  It also led him to introduce me to the work,
which his former students will recall how much he admired, of
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Maillart">
Robert Maillart 
</ulink>
and
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pier_Luigi_Nervi">
Pier Luigi Nervi
</ulink>
and many others.  Some of these ended up having a major effect on my own
teaching, in calculus and engineering classes, as might be noted elsewhere
in these notes.
</para>
<para>
To avoid possible confusion, I am not claiming that BG saw Maillart and
especially Nervi as major examples of wonderful architecture, as distiguished
from what I guess I will call "works of engineering".  But he could carefully
discuss the way in which Maillart's work clearly evolved from actual
real problems with elevation, construction, and temperature problems,
and how Nervi's forms had much to do with methods of construction and
problems (such as spanning large spaces without obvious supports).
Perhaps I did not realize as much at the time as I should have how
remarkable it was that this "designer" very very clearly understood
the physical underpinnings of his work.
</para>
<note>
In preparing this note I have run across what appears to be a nice explanation
of Gaudi's dynamic approach which I described as "strings in the basement"
with Nervi's more analytic (and thus somewhat static) approach in an article
by Charles Jencks in the July 2000 Architectural Review under the tile
"Jenck's theory of evolution an overview of twentieth-century architecture".
I can say that I suspect Mr. Goff would heartily agree with the statement that
Gaudi was "the best architect of the century", and not, as too many people
would suspect from Goff, because he did "wild forms", but because, as Jencks
says of his "creative brilliance at turning city structures and buildings
into a high art", and the remainder of the reasons that Jencks adduces.
BG spoke often about almost exactly the difference between Gaudi and Nervi
and how he makes "form-types" "his own" and we literally discussed things
like hyperbolic parabaloids in that sense (unfortunately I did not know
enough about engineering, and the American contractors we encountered did not
know enough about construction, to do anything with them).  We did at one point
discuss trying to follow Nervi's lead a bit and get involved in a design-constrruction setting exactly in order to be able to try such things.
</note>
</section>
<section>
<title>Organic architecture</title>
<note>
<para>
We are going to be making some distinctions between terms.
Professional mathematicians (and I hope I am one) eat terms
for breakfast, lunch, and dinner, so I am not very good at insisting
upon what terms mean: you can define them any way you want,
all my job requires is that I must follow your definition
if I claim to be following it. But I cannot then turn around and
claim it means something else.
</para>
<para>
Alfred North Whitehead (my creative "God" in the same way as Debussy
was to Goff) in describing relativity after Einstein said something
like "We claim that space and time are abstractions from reality. If they
are then produced that abstraction piece by piece.  At the moment
science is setting out on a fishing expedition to see if we can find
something that we call the measurement of space and something that we
can call the measurement of time, and the only reason given for this
is a sentimental regard for Galileo, Euler, Newton, and Lagrange."
That is the way I feel about much of the terminology we use to
describe architecture.  I have no right to claim that I have described
Goff's feelings, but would be quite willing to place a bet.
</para>
</note>
<para>
In the light of the above note I am going to describe a few different
ways in which "organic" might be meant, and am not willing to spend
even a moment discussing whether they are "correct" or not.  Like in
"Alice in Wonderland" words mean what I say they  mean for me, nothing
more and nothing less.  You can have your words have whatever meaning
you like.
</para>
<formalpara>
<title>The solution of a problem</title>
<para>
and if  you know your Sullivan you will say "lies in the problem
itself".  Of course that is not the exact quote from
<ulink
url="http://www.njit.edu/v2/Library/archlib/pub-domain/sullivan-1896-tall-bldg.html">The tall office building artistically considered</ulink>,
the article that "started it all" in many opinions, but it is the aspect
I wish to consider for the moment. This follows the thinking of many
great American thinkers such as Emerson who preceded Sullivan
(i Have a bias toward Emerson since my great-grandfather William Allison
published his first works in New York). 
A number of us who worked with
BG recall that although his respect for Wright was enormous in many ways
he seemed even more attuned to Louis Sullivan (and you have not lived
unless you have had a personal tour through a Sullivan bank with him,
or a discussion of Sullivan's drawings, even working drawings). 
</para>
<para>
Sullivan's actual phrase was of course "it is of the very essence of every problem that it contains and suggests its own solution".
Later in the article a consequence
of the phrase was set forth as "Form ever follows function" (later
the "ever" disappeared from the phrase and following that disappearance
would lead us on an interesting trail we are not going to follow.
This (in my unsophisticated and uneducated notions) is where "form"
became a fixation.
</para>
<para>
Going back to the original and more general form leads us toward
"problem solving" and "form" is a major component of many solutions,
but not all, and is also not the only component. So we will
continue this thread of discussion in a bit. But "organic" in
this context means related to deriving solutions from problems.
</para>
<para>
Another sense of the term "organic" relates to nature.  Wright of
course is a major figure in relation to this meaning: "each building
must respond to nature" and "each building must have its own Nature"
(the latter meaning more perhaps than the first, but to me usually
a mystical attachment to nature is part). There is a bit less about
"the problem" in any sense other perhaps blending with the site.
</para>
<para>
A third sense of "organic" also has its roots perhaps in Sullivan
as it refers to "ornament" and to a degree with Wright in "the nature
of the material".  It just a bit later also is seen in the ideas of
Gaudi, but also blended with "structure" in a much stronger way
than with the first two architects. 
</para>
<para>
So my intent is to see if we can follow for a bit these various directions
in the work of Bruce Goff.  My contention (lets just call it observation
and leave it at that: its not my field, and I have no right to contend:
as a mathematician you either just notice or else you actually have to
prove, and there is no conclusion to be forced upon us so nothing to prove.
</para>
</formalpara>
</section>
<section>
<title>Design by system</title>
<para>
So many architects end up figuring out a way to do something once, and
fall in love with that (or perhaps with the publicity their early creations
produce) and decide that "this is the way it should be done". They then
begin to elaborate what they think they did (and are not actually very
good judges, or even very truthful, about that), and come up with a "system"
that becomes "the way you should work".
</para>
<para>
For what seems to me (especially as an actual mathematician and teacher
of systems design) they and their work are then described as
"systematic" and seen as examples of what serious folks should do.
My notion is that the exact opposite is the case: they are imposing
an aesthetic preference upon the problem and ignoring much of it in
order to make sure that it does "fit their system".
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Design as "pure art"</title>
<para>
So if you now believe that BG did not follow a "system", and use perhaps
terms such as "individualistic" or "iconolastic" to describe his process
(or lack thereof in your view) then you typically one of two camps:
his work can be dismissed as that of a minor artist who was important
only because a few striking designs, but did not produce anything of
great significance for others to "follow" (the word he seemed to hate
more than any other), or you decide "he was great, his goal was to
show all of us the possibilities for forms, and free us up in design
for the future" ("form-giver" is a term he was good at ridiculing,
with his well-known penchant for puns).
</para>
<para>
To me the truth (or part of the portion I was able to discern), and one
that along with others I observed on a daily basis as he worked, is that
he was a "problem-solver" in the "organic" sense of that word.  Now
"organic" back then, and perhaps now, was a word like "green" is now:
you had to attach it to be "good", but God help you if your "good" was 
not what someone else had in mind.  Back then it somehow seemed to end up
associated primarily with nature (much in the sense that Wright, a great
architect of course, meant it: "honor the site, honor the nature of the
materials", and so on - these are precepts that BG as much as anyone
believed to be important, but to many of us he went much further).
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optimal design</title>
<para>
Although BG and I discussed the design process many times at length,
to my sadness we never discussed this particular topic.  "Optimal"
anything was not a subject he was likely to ever bring up, and at the
time I was not a mature enough mathematician to be able to "bring him out"
on the topic.
</para>
<para>
I assumed, like most of us, that his lack of interest in such a topic
was a product of his lack of a "scientific" side and the predominance
of his "artistic" side.  We did spend a lot of time discussing mathematics,
mostly my explaining to him how to me it was the most creative of all
endeavors since there were literally no constraints other than those you
had deliberately created in your own mind.  Many of you may have heard
of Bertrand Russell's description of mathematics as a "meaningless
game played with meaningless symbols", but you most likely have never
heard that this description is in Russel's Autobiography as part of a
discussion with Alfred North Whitehead (who was Russell's mentor and
to me a far superior logician and a real mathematician - Russell was
a logician but never an actual mathematician).  At any rate Whitehead
said something like (this is my paraphrase): "To you mathematics is as
things appear at bright noonday when things are in sharp relief and
clearly distinguished from one another.  To me mathematics is as things
appear when you first wake in early morning. Everything is cloudy, things
merge into other things, nothing is clear, and it is the task of mathematics
to help us take this vague world and learn things that are concrete about
it".
</para>
<para>
My favorite term is "muddle" so BG and I discussed how this justified
"scientifically" a seemingly less precise and much more intuitive form
of design. I am aware that most who know BG have a hard time imagining
him engaged in this kind of discussion, and all I can say is it would have
been great if his remarks had been recorded: BG knew and understood so
much more than any of us realized when we knew him.
</para>
<para>
Later after I became a more professional mathematician, and especially at
a summer seminar I attended with a wonderful mathematician, I learned about
what I have always called "anti-optimization" theory, and in fact have always
wished (and wished only unfortunately) to develop lectures on the topic
(mathematical lectures are way too hard - you can't say "I think" you have
to produce actual examples and find hypotheses that lead to conclusions
under rigorous techniques of proof - it is a game, but has rigid rules).
One of the things I learned is that you can very very often prove in relation
to a certain problem that there may not be a solution (we all know that), but
more importantly when there is a solution that there may be  many, not one,
and that under whatever criteria you set up for evaluating the solution there
may not be a "best" - we say "optimal" - solution, and that even if we can
prove that an optimal solution must exist it may be we can also prove that
the cost of finding and implementing the optimal solution may far exceed
any advantage it has over just a plain old "solution", maybe over the
one you could come to rather easily  by just "following your nose".
</para>
<para>
What I learned from learning this (and most mathematical learning seems to
consist mostly in "chains of learning") is not the lesson that "you might
as well be lazy, it ain't worth it to figure out 'the right thing'",
but a very different lesson, "you have room to have many aspects of a
solution that were not specific conditions of the original problem".
</para>
<para>
Applied to architecture, and especially that of Mr. Goff with extreme
limits on budgets, limited understanding initially by clients, and on and
on, is that "you can add the condition of desirable and even highly
beautiful aesthetics" without "taking anything away". Of course his
justification, and the justification of many of us, is that the aesthetics
will end up being a very major measure of the satisfaction provided by
the solution.  It is well-known, and remarkable, that almost all of his
clients end up literally in love with the environment they provide and
will always tell you the difference the structure made in their lives.
They may (or may not in several cases that I became personally familiar
with) understand in advance that this would happen, and thus that any
form at all of specific aesthetic was never part of "the problem" when
design began, from their point of view.  And for that matter even if
willing they would have been unable to fund such a goal.
(Read Herb Greene's remarks about the Bavinger house: Gene added mostly
by his own hand and that of (amateur) student helpers the resources it
took to make the aesthetics possible, and could not imagine in advance
how much of those would be needed!)
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>
